United Association of Journeymen & Apprentices of Plumbers and Pipefitting Industry of the U.S. and Canada, Local 105; Records apap053
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
United Association of Journeymen And Apprentices of The Plumbing And Pipe Fitting Industry of The United States and Canada Local 105 Records
1893-1972
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipe Fitting Industry. Local 105 (Albany, NY)
apap053
1.6 cubic ft.
United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and PipeFitting Industry of the United States and Canada, Local 105 Records document the regular business of this chapterof the union, including meetings, financial reports, grievance reports, and membership.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were lent to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, for preservation photocopying by UA Local 105 as a part of the Harry Van Arsdale, Jr., Labor History Project. The originals have been returned to Local 105.
Organizational Sketch
The beginnings of the United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipefitting Industry of the United States and Canada is traced to 1889, when a Boston plumber named P. J. Quinlan addressed a brief letter to Richard A. O'Brien, a plumber in Washington, D.C. The author of the letter became the first General President and its recipient the first General Secretary-Treasurer of the United Association. Prior to 1889, those plumbers, steamfitters and gas fitters who were organized were members of independent local unions with either no affiliation, or affiliation with a variety of trades. By 1889 existing organizations were declining or becoming devoted to only one craft, so local union leaders began to consider other ways to unite national pipe trades journeymen to deal with mutual problems, including how to treat traveling members, build apprenticeships, and provide strike aid. In response to these issues, the United Association was officially born on October 11, 1889. The original name of the organization was the United Association of Journeymen Plumbers, Gas Fitters, Steam Fitters and Steam Fitters' Helpers of the United States and Canada. The union grew from forty delegates representing twenty-three unions in ten states to an international union representing almost 300,000 members in more than 400 local unions throughout the United States and Canada.[1]
The first meeting of the United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipefitting Industry of the United States and Canada, Local 105 was held on March 23, 1893. The union was chartered on May 1, 1893 as Local 105 of Schenectady County, New York. Local 376 of Amsterdam, New York merged with Local 105 on September 27, 1962. Local 253 of Gloversville, New York merged with Local 105 on May 1, 1972.
Notes []1] UA History, http://www.ua.org/history.htm, accessed 27 January 2003 [see http://www.ua.org/history.asp, 21 February 2005].
Scope and Contents
The collection includes meeting minutes from Locals 105 and 253 of the United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipefitting Industry of the United States and Canada. The minutes include accounts the unions' regular meetings as well as related material also entered into the ledgers. There are some officer and membership lists, correspondence, financial reports, grievance reports, and additional items produced by the union during the course of conducting their regular business.
For additional labor collections in the Department, see the online Labor subject guide at http://library.albany.edu/speccoll/labor.htm.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is composed of two series containing similar materials and content.
Schenectady, New York; Labor; Labor unions--New York (State)--Albany; Plumbers--New York (State)--Albany; Labor unions--History--19th century; Labor unions--History--20th century; New York (State); Minutes; Administrative records; Financial Records; Membership lists; Correspondence; United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipe Fitting Industry, Local 105; United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipe Fitting Industry, Local 253; United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipe Fitting Industry
- Local 105 Minutes, 1893-1902; 1907-1927; 1932; 1943; 1949-1961; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1: Local 105 Minutes is composed of photocopies of union ledgers from Local 105.
  - Minutes, 1893-1898 (Box 1 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1899-1900 (Box 1 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1900-1902 (Box 1 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1907-1909 (Box 1 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1909-1910 (Box 1 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1910-1913 (Box 1 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1913-1914 (Box 1 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1914-1915 (Box 1 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1915-1916 (Box 1 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1916-1917 (Box 2 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1918-1919 (Box 2 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1919-1920 (Box 2 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1920-1921 (Box 2 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1921-1922 (Box 2 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1922-1924 (Box 2 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1924-1927 (Box 2 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 7)
  - Minutes and Historical, 1932; 1943 (Box 2 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1949-1951 (Box 3 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1951-1953 (Box 3 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1953-1955 (Box 3 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1950-1952 (Box 3 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 3 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1954-1956 (Box 3 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1956-1958 (Box 3 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1958-1960 (Box 3 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1960-1961 (Box 3 (1-Local 105 Minutes, ), Folder 9)
- Financials, 1911-2007; Undated; 2
  Series 2: Local 253 Minutes is composed of photocopies of Local 253's ledgers.
  - Minutes, 1955-1958 (Box 4 (2-Financials), Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1958-1961 (Box 4 (2-Financials), Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1961-1964 (Box 4 (2-Financials), Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1964-1965 (Box 4 (2-Financials), Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1965-1966 (Box 4 (2-Financials), Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1966-1967 (Box 4 (2-Financials), Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1967-1969 (Box 4 (2-Financials), Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1969-1971 (Box 4 (2-Financials), Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1971-1972 (Box 4 (2-Financials), Folder 9)